[Music]
hi and welcome to this session on fixed
and variable G allocations my name is
Brian Nelson I'm a program manager with
the business Central team and with me I
have
hello everyone my name is Nicola and I'm
a software developer in the business
Central Development team this session is
about uh a new feature called GL
allocations and what we will do today is
talk a bit about what it is then we'll
show you uh a demo of the feature and
Nica will take you through how you set
up the feature for the different types
of allocations you can do and then
lastly uh Nicolai will give you some
tips and tricks or some back ground
insights into how it's done and what it
work with and what it doesn't work with
so uh let's just jump into it so in last
release we introduced a new feature
called statistical accounts and that is
a feature that can hold nonfinancial
numerical data that you can then use for
analysis or
reporting or other purposes and built in
it works with the financial reporting uh
feature where you can create as is shown
on the screen you can create reports
that use the statistical accounts to
create some kpis uh that are not based
on only uh your accounting data in this
case it's a number of employees for
example uh let's just take a a brief
look in the in the product and see where
it is so in
here under statistical
accounts you can find or you can set up
uh different statistical accounts and
basically it's h we can open one of them
number of employees it's a nice number
to
track um you can see it you can open the
balance to see what have you entered so
far and I know that it's up here we'll
change the monthly change and then we'll
skip up a bit and you can see that I
typed in some uh
changes uh to the statistical account
and you basically type it them in like
you do a journal except that it it can
be one-sided there's no debit and credit
you just type in a number and register
it and you can use dimensions for it and
when you've done that you can now start
using it in for example the financial
reporting
module and you can run a report like
employee per Revenue per employee and
you can get some numbers that use this
together with your accounting data to
produce some
kpis but with this uh release we have
introduced uh a new feature that you can
also use statistical accounts for the
new feature is called allocation
accounts and it's used for Distributing
or allocating uh cost and revenue
there's a fixed type where you can um
Define how you share a a line
item for example if you're splitting up
the rent uh per department and you have
already decided on What percentages goes
to what dimension value you can do that
in in the fix
type um we just saw the statistical
accounts with employee head count if
you're having an event training for
example you can split up the the line
item per the statistical account per di
menion for example if you filter so that
you have a a more Dynamic uh
allocation and to make it a little
simpler um we have also included an
inherit uh property or type where you
basically take any account that you're
using and then start allocating it
instead of creating one for for each
type we'll see that in a
second the feature also works with
deferrals uh and it works in um in
recurring Journal also it works in
general journals and as we will see it
also works in documents so let's let's
go and look at at some of the
the things it can do for you one of the
things you you sometimes want to do is
you post your rent for example or you
post training and you do it through a
journal this is the simple
example so we have some lines here where
I can show you the different
concepts we have one line here for end
of May where you had an audit in the
beginning of the year and now you want
to allocate it and um when you do it you
pick the allocation
account the new type that you can select
in the journal here at the bottom and
then you pick one of the available um
allocations account that you have set up
in this case I've set up one
specifically for auditing because we
have decided when we did the budget for
the year like which department gets
which um audit expenses so if we zoom in
on on this one we'll just zoom in the
the
report so now we only have this one and
then we can take a preview instead of
just posting
it I have one line but in my business I
have three companies uh three divisions
uh departments Dimension and you can see
when I post it it will get split into
three individual lines and of course
there's a debit and credit so we end up
with six GL accounts and they will be
posted to each individual dimensions
that I have it's not obvious how I've
done it we'll see that in a second but
I've already decided what the allocation
should be and uh the system will will
then split it up for me another type uh
could be if you're allocating the rent
expense and you do it not just by a
fixed
um uh allocation because maybe you have
office baces that change over the year
and you keep track of that in the
statistical account so you want to use a
different allocation key uh and in this
case you still pick the allocation key
but you will pick another one and uh
this one we'll see that in in a second
it's actually using the employee number
uh to distribute it so again if we
filter and we take the preview same as
before I have one line I have three
departments I'll get six uh G lines
because it's splits it in three and a
debit credit uh you can see the numbers
are different the amount was a bit
different but if I do this over time I
will also uh get different results
because my office space Maybe I rent
some extra space Maybe I reduce my
production space office space and that
will determine the allocation so it's
it's a dynamic way of of doing it
allocation is done uh because you want
better uh data for uh a later analysis
of of your your business and how it's
it's progressing either as profit Center
cost center or or or both um setting up
allocation accounts obviously saves you
a lot of time that you don't have to
spend uh splitting up the uh the revenue
or or cost lines to save a lot of time
you can also uh use a third type called
inherit from parent that is set up and
you can see I have a an expense account
for software licenses and I picked that
but I picked the GL account not the
allocation sorry not the allocation
account this time because I don't want
to set up an allocation account for each
GL account where I have expense and
revenue that I want to distribute maybe
just some of them so it's easier to
recognize them in this case I put in the
uh account and here further to the right
you can see I can now select
uh to distribute per employee headcount
in this case it makes sense to do it per
employee that's the one that are using
my software that I bought and the
licenses so I'll split it
up and now if we do a
preview you can see it works like before
you have six lines but this time I
didn't set it up we'll see it in a
second I didn't set it up in advance for
for this particular account I selected
the account and that will save you a lot
of time um but maybe also be a less
transparent way of of allocating as you
can see uh if I pick deferrals I've set
up a deferral that will split it in into
three uh periods the next uh three
periods um in this case it will be
August uh September and October because
I'm posting in
July um if I do this just to see that it
works
I'll get a a ton of new lines uh because
it will split up each line and then it
will do the Furrs for for that and you
can see if we scroll up a bit it has the
admin here it has 10 lines for that the
first is the I split it up so I post
that I take it out again and put it into
the um the acral account that I've using
for for deferrals and then I I defer
uh for three different periods so the
new feature works with
deferral and one last
example so in a purchase invoice you can
also use allocation accounts maybe
you're getting a purchase invoice and um
and it's something that you want to
allocate so again you pick the
allocation account you pick the
allocation that you want to do let's say
we got the uh the rent payment as a new
invoice and we want to distribute it so
we pick this one and then we can type in
quantity one and an amount for
example so this is all good I can now
use it in U in documents sales and
purchase and I can use it in general
journals um sometimes you have an
allocation that is predefined that
you're okay with but sometimes you want
to to make an adjustment before you post
and in this case we have a line
you can go in on the functions and
redistribute allocation account and you
have a distribution but if you're not
happy um you can simply just change
it and minus
1 we'll say
300 and and we're good you can also say
okay but actually I want to um to post
something else to maybe a different
account uh what do we have we have an
account here for heating part of the uh
the invoice was for heating so I'll take
200 here and then I'll reduce this one
so I can add
lines the lines will be posted as a
journal line and of course when you are
here you can go in and change the
default Dimensions we had the the
predefined one that has admin maybe you
just want to dump all the expenses for
sales in this one so you can go in and
and override it you can also say this
one let's take a look this is production
but this um it's not the production
facility so we'll just delete this
line take it away then we are a bit
short on um on the amount but we'll fix
that here we go and so you can overwrite
all the elements that that goes into uh
defining a a cost
allocation and this also works in uh
General journals
and then you commit the changes and that
will be used when you posted the
document so you've seen how it works
you've seen instead of posting it we we
looked at the previews so you got a
glimpse of what is the end result now
Nicola will take you through how you set
up these individual uh types of
allocation accounts all right over to
you Nicola thank you br so if you would
like to set up the allocation accounts
and use the nice scenarios that Brian
has just Dem mode the easiest way is
just to go to the allocations account
list like here they're also accessible
through lookups or through the
statistical account page as well and
here you can see that we are having
predefined accounts that Brian has used
in his demo but I'm going to create one
from the scratch to show you how does
the process look like end to end so
let's create the allocation account for
the
expenses and here I'm going to use the
this account number so for leases I
would also like to use the rent and I
would also like to split all of the
costs that are coming to let's say this
account and this is electricity for
rental so as you can see as I have typed
it in it has equally split it into the
percentages and now you can change this
one by defining share and this is a UI
pattern that we are using in the
business Central which which helps you
to change the percentages in an easy way
and ensure that they are always adding
up to 100 so let's say that this one
goes to 50% and this one goes to 30% and
this one goes to 20% so you have seen I
have quickly edited and tweaked the
percentages without the need to do
anything and we ensured that all of the
numbers are adding up to 100% also if I
would like to change to 55 and this one
to 25 I can now see that all of the
numbers are actually matching and that
it is adding to
100% additional nice way of using the
share is if you are having whole numbers
let's say that you're holding a bill in
the hand so let's say that this one
costed
1,525 and this one costed
555 and this one costed
39 34 it's going to calculate the
percentages automatically for you one
thing that that I would like to point
your attention to is if you select about
this page the UI is going to show you
the whole percent but in the background
we are calculating it up to five
decimals so these calculations are going
to be very accurate and we are also
going to be using amount rounding when
we are allocating to the specific GN
lines but percentage thems is rather
accurate if you don't want this you can
simply just change these numbers that
the system has calculated for you and
enter 76 23 and two so you're always
going to get these
percentages then next thing which is
very useful is that you can Define the
dimensions so let's say that we want to
say that this one is coming with the
business group office always so if you
define it like this whenever we are
creating G lines out of the main G line
we will ensure that it has the business
group that has the office Dimension
assigned to it so this one is going to
be added on the top and it is going to
win so you can do that to all of the
lines
here and you can also change the
dimensions so they are going to follow
the line that they are assigned to so if
you would like to add something here
right like an area it's possible to be
done as
well and the last thing that you can do
on this page is that you can test the
allocations so if I open this page and
if you remember what I said about the
decimals and if I had a higher number
here you will see that the Precision is
being used and you will see
approximately what is the amount that is
going to be post
posted so this was all about the fixed
allocation accounts so you can use these
if you have fixed percentages that you
want to split the amounts between the
second one which is very useful in my
opinion is the variable allocation
account and let's say that we want to
split the cost of employee per
department and here I'm going to select
that the account is variable and now I'm
getting slightly different UI for the
destination account let's pick one here
and let's select something like
transport cars and other transport let's
say that we want to split this one and
we can use the GL account as the input
so it's going to take the balance of the
GL account to calculate the percentage
from but in this case let's use the
statistical account and let's count on
the number of employees here
so here you can specify how you are
calculating the balance it can either be
a balance set date fiscal year week
quarter previous year you can see that
we have a lot of options and the reason
for this is because we used the same
options that we have on the cost
allocations so we assume that it is
going to be useful most likely some of
them are not needed and we are probably
missing few so if you have any feedback
please let us know and the last thing
that you can do here is that you can
specify a filter we offer filtering on
the global Dimensions so let's say that
here I want to filter on all of the
employees that are in the administration
department so for the next line I would
like to do the same setup right and it's
going to be statistical accounts
employees again and this time I'm
filtering on the department which is
production and as the last line I'm
going to repeat the
same and I'm going to specify the filter
to be
sales
as I did in the previous example I would
want to specify the department here to
be
aimed because then when you're posting
it's going to create the dimensions and
it will ensure that the totals that are
created from the posting code unit are
correct I made a mistake here so I'll go
back and change it to
prod and as the last one I'm going to
set
sales so now each time when I use this
allocation account it's going to post to
this distribution account number and it
will split the values it's going to
assign the dimensions
automatically and you will get the
accurate calculation based on the number
of employees on the day that you have
selected for posting here it is very
useful to test the allocation because if
you select this value you can see how it
is Distributing the amounts so you can
see that it is using filters it knows
how many employees are per department
and it's going to show you how the cost
is going to be allocated so that was all
for the variable account type if you
would like to use inherit from parent
then we cannot Define the destination
account number so these needs to be
blank don't enter them and the only
thing that you need to do here is to
select inherit from parent and then you
can select this account on the line
specify the g account as brand has shown
you and we are going to use that account
to automatically fill the destination
account number so this is going to help
you with defining less allocation
accounts because then you can reuse it
for anything that you want to split
based on the number of
employees all right so that was all for
the setup and for the last part I'm
going to show you the how the code works
and explain some inner workings of the
features so you can understand how you
can use it better also if you're a
developer and you would like to extended
this is the part where we are going to
explain how the inner workings work so
here uh the allocation account is
actually implemented in the base app and
it is going to be under Financial
Management's allocation account folder
so we have grouped all of the objects
that are related to the allocation
accounts here and there are three code
units which we are using to integrate
with the rest of the product
functionality the first one is general
journal account management which is
handling all of the logic with
integration with General
journals we have sales allocation
account management which is allocating
sales and the last one is allocating
purchase so this is doing the
integration with the purchase management
the main point of integration is when
you try to post a batch the thing that
we are going to do is that first we are
going to verify if the lines are correct
that the user has entered and then we
are going to create the lines from
bch so the thing that we do is that we
take a g line and then depending on how
many allocation lines you have that's
the number of the new general journal
lines that we are going to
create and here the thing that I would
like to point your attention to is that
if you go to the create lines so we just
going to navigate deep in the
code so you can see all of the parts
that are doing
here so under the create G
line
so here is the actual code which is
doing the split we have added the
integration events two of them one is on
before create General joural line which
you can use if you are having any other
functionality which should be split so
if you're having custom quantities or
the custom amounts that we are not
handling within this code this is the
subscriber that you should subscribe to
to split these values across the lines
if you need to split them
the second event that we recommend
subscribing to is on before verify so if
you have any kind of functionality that
should not be compatible with allocation
accounts this is the event that you can
use to throw an error and to stop the
posting okay so that was all on my
side thank you
Nichola so um hopefully a feature that
will help you save a lot of uh data
entry and a feature that will give you
uh data to do more analysis of how
business is going thank you for joining
this
session thank you on my side as
well